Steve J. Cavallari Papers VHP2005/3
CCSU Veterans History Project
Steve J. Cavallari Papers
Bulk, 1942-1945
1942 - 1945, 2005
VHP2005/3
CCSU Veterans History Project
86.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This Collection details Steve Cavallari’s experincein World War II. He was drafted into the Army Air Service where he attended driver training and became a heavy truck driver. He served with the 360th Air Service Group in Papua New Guinea, Australia, and the Philippines. The Collection contains copies of service records, typed notes taken during the interview, and Black and white photographs taken in the Pacific by Steve Cavallari during his tour of duty in the army
Cavallari, Steve J., 1918 -
Conditions Governing Access note
None
Biographical/Historical note
Steve Cavallari was born in Italy near Lake Garda and moved to the United States at age 17, arriving on Thanksgiving Day, 1935. He was drafted into the U.S. Army Air Corps in early 1942. On the day he travelled to Fort Devens (MA) to begin his service, he took a spoon from the Bond Hotel in Hartford, which he has held onto for good luck ever since. Cavallari was then sent to Miami Beach for basic training, where the Army Air Corps established quarters at the Flamingo Hotel. From there he was transferred to Alabama, where he became the personal driver for an officer on the base. His unit was shipped to Amberely Field in Australia in a large convoy that departed from San Francisco. His unit then became part of a semi-permanent base that the Air Corps set up in Nadzab, New Guinea. Cavallari's duties on the base included driving trucks to deliver supplies as well as bartending in the officers' club. His unit was also sent to Moratai Island off of New Guinea for a time where they experienced heavy bombing from the Japanese, which resulted in a high number of casualties. It was also during this period that Cavallari met his wife while on leave in Australia, and they married during his third period of leave to Australia. He returned to the United States in August of 1945, immediately hopping a train to Avon, CT. Cavallari found work at the Fuller Brush Company in Hartford just seven days after his return, and worked there for the next 30 years.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
United States. Army Air Corps.; United States. Army Air Forces. Air Service Group, 360th.; Biak Island (Indonesia); Brisbane (Qld.); Clark Field (Philippines); Fort Devens (Mass.); Interviews; Manuscript; Miami Beach (Fla.); Military -- Leaves and furloughs; New Guinea; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii); Photographs; War brides -- Australia; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- New Guinea; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Paprs
  - Honorable discharge certificate, 24 September 1945; VHP2005/3.I.01
  - Army Separation Qualification Record, 27 September 1945; VHP2005/3.I.02
  - Enlisted Record and Report of Separation, September 1945; VHP2005/3.I.03
  - Interview synopsis, Apr. 15, 2005; VHP2005/3.I.4
- Series II:Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images
    - Hula dancer in Hawaii on the way to New Guinea, 1942; VHP2005/3.II.1
    - Aerial shot of New Guinea, circa 1942; VHP2005/3.II.2
    - Papua Hotel in Port Moresby, New Guinea, 1942; VHP2005/3.II.3
    - Aerial photo of New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.4
    - New Guinea village. A Captain from Australia was in charge of the village, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.5
    - Typical village hut, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.6
    - Anti-aircraft gun left behind by Japanese when American forces overtook the area, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.7
    - Guns and artillery left behind when American forces overtook the area, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.8
    - Anti-aircraft gun left behind by Japanese, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.9
    - Wrecked Japanese aircraft, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.10
    - Steve Cavallari with other American servicemen and natives. Left to right: Steve Cavallari, Frank Turnbelt, and Captain Martin, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.11
    - Steve Cavallari and an unknown soldier, Port Moresby, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.12
    - Steve Cavallari with natives, New Guinea, circa 1943; VHP2005/3.II.13
    - Three native men. Photo titled “fuzzy wuzzy”, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.14
    - Native children, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.15
    - Training plane, New Guinea, 1943; VHP2005/3.II.16
    - Red Cross plane landing, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.17
    - Japanese soldiers surrendering pose for a photo (according to photo log), 1944; VHP2005/3.II.18
    - Unnamed Air Corps Officer, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.19
    - Three of Steve Cavallari’s friends, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.20
    - Soldiers jumping out of foxhole, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.21
    - American airplanes being repaired, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.22
    - American G.I., New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.23
    - Group of enlisted men. Steve Cavallari front left, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.24
    - Steve Cavallari on board C-46 (plane) from Australia to New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.25
    - P-38 fighter plane landing in Nadzab, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.26
    - Landing at Morotai Island, Papua New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.27
    - Pin-up girl painted on the side of a B-24, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.28
    - Pin-up girl painted on the side of a B-24, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.29
    - Steve Cavallari the day after his wedding, Australia, June 8, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.30
    - Native village policeman, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.31
    - Group of native village policemen, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.32
    - 3 native village policemen, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.33
    - Native girls, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.34
    - Native girls, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.35
    - Young native girl, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.36
    - New Guinea Soldier, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.37
    - Group of natives posing with several service men next to 'Garamut'(slit-drum), New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.38
    - Three New Guinea natives in ceremonial attire with headdresses, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.39
    - American Corporal with three natives, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.40
    - Natives and water buffalo rice planting, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.41
    - Natives and water buffalo rice planting, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.42
    - Four native children, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.43
    - Native village huts built on stilts in the water. Always a lot of dogs, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.44
    - Australian officer with group of natives in ceremonial attire, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.45
    - Natives, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.46
    - Portrait of four native girls in grass skirts, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.47
    - Natives engaged in a game of tug-of-war, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.48
    - Native child in ceremonial attire during celebration, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.49
    - Group of young native boys, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.50
    - Large gathering of natives for celebration, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.51
    - Native village, huts and boats, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.52
    - Five people near a large hut, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.53
    - Native village built on stilts on dry ground, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.54
    - Native picking coconuts, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.55
    - Young native girl in grass skirt, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.56
    - New Guinea regatta (entertainment), 1944; VHP2005/3.II.57
    - Native evacuating a New Guinea village, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.58
    - Young native girl, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.59
    - Group of natives, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.60
    - Children on the road to village, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.61
    - Native child playing cricket, New Guinea, 1944; VHP2005/3.II.62
    - American anti-aircraft guns, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.63
    - Crashed Japanese airplanes, Maffin Bay New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.64
    - American soldier nicknamed “Alabama” standing next to an elaborately carved totem pole, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.65
    - Steve Cavallari (right) with an unknown serviceman, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.66
    - Mess Hall, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.67
    - Steve Cavallari (left) and Sergeant Hudzina (right) leaning on Jenny the jeep, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.68
    - Two servicemen standing next to the sign: 345th Bomb Group Headquarters / Tree Top Terrors, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.69
    - American military cemetery, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.70
    - Troops landing from LST at Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.71
    - Landing at Philippines, Steve Cavallari arrived on ship #696, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.72
    - Unloading of Steve Cavallari’s ship #696 during landing at Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.73
    - American fighter planes. B24 in the foreground, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.74
    - American base, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.75
    - Church at Clark Field, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.76
    - Bombed building, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.77
    - Bombed building, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.78
    - Active street scene with inhabitants and carts, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.79
    - Street scene in front of gated building, Philippines, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.80
    - Road from Nadzab to Lea built by Americans, New Guinea, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.81
    - Steve’s war bride Ida Gauiglio Cavallari (identified by the arrow) onboard the ship Mariposa leaving Brisbane, Australia bound for America. Steve was already in the United States, 1945; VHP2005/3.II.82
  - Subseries B: Moving Images
    - Oral history interview, Apr. 15, 2005; VHP2005/3.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd; August, Robert B., (Robert Burton), 1921 -; Vincent, Roche (Disk DVD VHP2005/3, Box VHP Interview #1)